Pengcheng Zhao, PhD (Beihang University, BUAA)

- ≥ zhaopc@buaa.edu.cn
- (852) 51312272
- **G** https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=tUOE-8IAAAAJ
- HJ805, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, 11 Yuk Choi Road, Hung Hom, Kowloon, Hong Kong

About me

I am currently a postdoctoral fellow at the Hong Kong Polytechnic University (PolyU). My research interests focus on laser spectroscopy, fiber-optic sensors and devices. I've participated in 4 research grants, published 10 peer-reviewed papers such as *Nature Comm., Laser Photonics Rev.*, and *Opt. Lett.*, and co-authored 3 national patents. Throughout my academic career, I was the recipient of numerous national scholarships and awards, including "China's Top 10 Optical Breakthrough in 2020".

Employment History

04/2022 - now

Postdoctoral Fellow in collaboration with Prof. Jin Wei and Prof. A. Ping Zhang at Department of Electrical Engineering, **PolyU**, Hong Kong, China.

07/2017 - 01/2021

Research Assistant in Prof. Jin Wei group (PhD Joint Supervision) at Department of Electrical Engineering, **PolyU**, Hong Kong, China.

Education

09/2015 - 01/2022

PhD in Engineering (after o9/2017) & Master study in Engineering (before o9/2017) (Supervisor: Prof. Shangchun Fan), School of Instrumentation and Optoelectronic Engineering, BUAA, China.

Thesis title: Investigation on fiber-optic photothermal interferometry for high sensitivity gas detection.

09/2011 - 07/2015

Bachelor of Engineering, College of Instrumentation & Electrical Engineering, **Jilin University**, China.

Research Publications (Selected)

Journal Articles

- **P. Zhao**†, K. V. Krishnaiah†, L. Guo, *et al.*, "Ultraminiature optical fiber-tip 3d-microprinted photothermal interferometric gas sensors," *Advanced Photonics*, Submitted, 2023.
- L. Guo, **P. Zhao***, H. L. Ho, *et al.*, "Pump-probe-alternating photothermal interferometry for two-component gas sensing," *Optics Letters*, Accepted, 2023.
- **P. Zhao***, H. L. Ho, S. Fan, and W. Jin*, "Evanescent wave lab-on-fiber for high sensitivity gas spectroscopy with wide dynamic range and long-term stability," *Laser & Photonics Reviews*, p. 2 200 972, 2023.
- **P. Zhao**, H. L. Ho, W. Jin*, S. Fan*, S. Gao, and Y. Wang, "Hollow-core fiber photothermal methane sensor with temperature compensation," *Optics Letters*, vol. 46, no. 11, pp. 2762–2765, 2021.
- **P. Zhao**, H. L. Ho, W. Jin*, *et al.*, "Gas sensing with mode-phase-difference photothermal spectroscopy assisted by a long period grating in a dual-mode negative-curvature hollow-core optical fiber," *Optics Letters*, vol. 45, no. 20, pp. 5660–5663, 2020.
- **P. Zhao**, Y. Zhao, H. Bao, *et al.*, "Mode-phase-difference photothermal spectroscopy for gas detection with an anti-resonant hollow-core optical fiber," *Nature communications*, vol. 11, no. 1, pp. 1–8, 2020.

Conference Proceedings

- 1 L. Guo, **P. Zhao***, H. L. Ho, *et al.*, "Two-component photothermal gas sensor with a pump-probe-alternating technique," in *Optical Fiber Sensors*, Optica Publishing Group, 2023, (Poster, Accepted).
- **P. Zhao**[†], K. V. Krishnaiah[†], L. Guo, *et al.*, "High-sensitivity fiber-tip photothermal gas sensor based on a 3d μ-printed fabry-pérot microcavity," in *Optical Fiber Sensors*, Optica Publishing Group, 2023, (Oral, Accepted).
- **P. Zhao**, S. Fan, H. L. Ho, and W. Jin*, "Microfiber evanescent-wave photothermal methane sensor with sub-ppm sensitivity," in *Optical Fiber Sensors*, Optica Publishing Group, 2022, Th3–5.
- **P. Zhao***, H. L. Ho, W. Jin, *et al.*, "Lpo1-lp11 mode conversion in a negative curvature hollow-core fiber by use of a long-period grating," in *Asia Communications and Photonics Conference*, Optica Publishing Group, 2020, M4A–118.
- **P. Zhao***, Y. Zhao, H. Bao, *et al.*, "Ultrasensitive photothermal gas sensor with a dual-mode anti-resonant hollow-core fiber," in *Optical Fiber Sensors*, Optica Publishing Group, 2020, W3–7.

Project Experiences

01/2019 to 12/2023

Microstructured hollow-core optical fiber multi-component trace gas analyzer National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) National Major Project for Research Instrument Development(61827820), HK\$7m (Participation).

07/2017 to 10/2018

Research on Optical Fiber Angle Sensor Based on Graphene Diaphragm Joint Supervision Scheme with the Chinese Mainland, Taiwan and Macao Universities(1-ZVG4), HK\$180,600 (Leader).

Awards and Achievements

- The Best Doctoral Thesis Award of BUAA, Beihang University
- The Best Doctoral Thesis Award of CSAA, The Nomination Award, Chinese Society of Aeronautics and Astronautics
- 2021 China's Top 10 Optical Breakthroughs, Chinese Laser Press
 - **Top 10 Outstanding Graduate Students**, Beihang University
 - **CASC Scholarship**, China Aerospace Science and Technology Corporation
- National scholarship for postgraduate student, Ministry of Education and Finance of the People's Republic of China
 - First prize for "Tanghui Electronics" inspirational scholarship, China Instrument and Control Society
- First prize for China Innovation & Entrepreneurship International Competition, China Instrument and Control Society

Skills

Languages Strong reading, writing and speaking competencies for English, Mandarin Chinese.

Coding C, Verilog, VHDL, Python, LATEX

Software COMSOL, Matlab, Labview, Mathamatica